<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en" /><updated>2024-01-25T06:40:12-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design.
</subtitle><entry><title type="html">My brain</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2024/My-Brain/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My brain" /><published>2024-01-15T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2024-01-15T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2024/My-Brain</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2024/My-Brain/"><![CDATA[<p>Image has been resampled. If slicer tool does not appear, try refreshing the page.</p>

<p>Volume Slicer Tool used: <a href="https://brainbrowser.cbrain.mcgill.ca">BrainBrowser</a>.</p>

<h1 id="preamble">Preamble</h1>
<p>Over the last 5 years (from the time of writing this), I’ve been collecting MRI scans of my body, participating in several scientific studies to obtain them. This <em>unusual</em> hobby has led me to 3D print a life-size model of my brain from a 7T scan. It’s always a hit when I bring the model to various classes or scientific outreach events.</p>

<p>These scans serve two purposes for me:
1) They offer a glimpse into the idiosyncracies of my body.
2) They offer a useful baseline for future medical reference.
This latter point is the most important one.</p>

<p>Most people undergo MRI scans only when health issues arise. Imagine a scenario where you start experiencing some supposed nerve-related back pain. If you were to go to the doctor amd get a diagnostic scan only at that point, the clinician may notice a disc bulge. This bulge would likely become the focus of attention. The doctor may advise you to undergo various treatments, some of which are quite invasive, such as surgery to remove the bulge - a solution that often provides only temporary relief. This is because when you remove the bulge, there is still a hole in the disc, allowing a new bulge to form.</p>

<p>Now this scenario isn’t just hypothetical. It was shared with me by a principal investigator who specializes in studying intervertebral disc degeneration. They described how they participated in their own studies for many decades and noticed the formation of a disc bulge. In some people this disc bulge could be a source of pain and discomfort they may be experiencing, however for them, they were completely asymptomatic.</p>

<p>Because they have records of previous scans, especially during times of general good health, showing the bulge existed even when they had no sympotoms, it changes the perspective. It doesn’t completely dismiss the bulge as a potential cause of any new pain, but it does encourage a more thorough consideration and analysis before reaching a diagnosis.</p>

<p>So if possible, try to collect your own scans, especially when you don’t necessarily need it. That said, interpret the scans with caution and always seek out a medical professional (or two) if there is any cause for concern.</p>

<h1 id="my-brain">My brain</h1>

<p>For now, please enjoy 3D model reconstructions of my brain. The very first image is a cortical segmented model that was used to 3D print my brain. The remainder are various levels of segmentation.</p>

<iframe src="../../../assets/plotly/brain.html" width="750" height="450" frameborder="0">
Loading brain model...
</iframe>
<p><a href="https://www.kartikpradeepan.com/assets/plotly/brain.html">Link to external view</a></p>

<h3 id="face-or-at-least-most-of-it-and-a-skull-stripped-whole-brain">Face (or at least most of it) and a skull stripped whole brain</h3>
<iframe src="../../../assets/plotly/face_raw.html" width="750" height="350" frameborder="0">
Loading face and skull model...
</iframe>
<p><a href="https://www.kartikpradeepan.com/assets/plotly/face_raw.html">Link to external view</a></p>

<p>Judging from the eyes in the left model, I may have been starting to fall asleep when I wasn’t supposed to. Also, I swear I have a mouth lol.</p>

<h3 id="white-matter-gray-matter-and-cerebrospinal-fluid">White matter, gray matter, and cerebrospinal fluid</h3>
<iframe src="../../../assets/plotly/white_gray_csf.html" width="750" height="350" frameborder="0">
Loading component models...
</iframe>
<p><a href="https://www.kartikpradeepan.com/assets/plotly/white_gray_csf.html">Link to external view</a></p>

<p><strong>White matter</strong>: Lies beneath the gray matter of the cortex and is composed predominantly of axons. Axons of neurons in white matter are coated with myelin, which is a fatty substance that helps increase the speed of signal transmission.</p>

<p><strong>Gray matter</strong>: Generally the outer layer of the brain, but also found in the deeper brain regions called nuclei. Crucial for processing and interpreting information. Involved in many functions such as motor control, sensory perception, memory, emotions, speech, decision-making, self-control, etc.</p>

<p><strong>Cerebrospinal fluid</strong>: Clear body fluid that is produced in the ventricles of the brain and flows around the central nervous system (both brain and spinal cord). Acts as a cushion, protecting the brain and spinal cord from injury. Additionally, helps maintain a stable environment by removing waste products from the brain, regulating the flow of nutrients, and maintaining intracranial pressure.</p>

<h3 id="various-details">Various details</h3>

<p>7T MRI of my brain taken on Dec 11, 2019.<br />
3T MRI of my brain taken on Aug 28, 2023.</p>

<p>T stands for Tesla representing the magnetic field strength of the MRI. Think of it like resolution. Higher tesla, higher resolution.</p>

<p>Most scans are T1-weighted, meaning they enhance fatty tissue and supress the signal from water. T2-weighted, on the other hand, enhances the water signal and are great for imaging CSF.</p>

<h3 id="if-youre-interested-in-doing-this-yourself">If you’re interested in doing this yourself</h3>
<p>For now, I won’t describe how to perform the skull stripping and segmentation from a nifti1 (.nii) file. That can be quite a labour-intensive process if you have no background in it. However, if you’re interested in converting .nii to .obj files and then producing Plotly plots like the ones above, you can see my code under the projects tab or <a href="/projects/PlotBrainOBJ">click here</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="personal" /><category term="neuroscience" /><category term="neuroscience" /><category term="personal" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[3D model and MRI of my various brain MRIs (warning - slow loading due to large downloads)]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">2023 Annual Letter</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2023/2023-Annual-Letter/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="2023 Annual Letter" /><published>2023-12-28T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2023-12-28T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2023/2023-Annual-Letter</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2023/2023-Annual-Letter/"><![CDATA[<p>Starting a tradition of writing an annual letter has been on my mind for quite some time, and this year it feels especially important as I’m at a pivotal juncture in my life. Previously, my years were predictable with school activities, research, attending conferences, etc. But this year is different: I’m finishing my PhD yet facing uncertainty in what comes next professionally. It’s a time for me to look ahead, stay open to opportunities, and navigate this new phase.</p>

<p>This past year was significant for me as I began to identify with a career in data science, a field I can see myself thriving in. However, the current economic climate is challenging, and the job market for data professionals is saturated. With elevated interest rates, companies are cutting back, and <em>experienced</em> data professionals are now looking for fewer available jobs. How can a recent PhD graduate break into the field?</p>

<p>2023 wasn’t just about these challenges, though; it brought its own set of opportunities. In November, I realized that I had developed a niche expertise in multielectrode array analyses for in vitro disease models. This realization, while specific and not relevant to 99.9% of people and companies, was a moment of personal pride that I am still savouring. That same month, this fact was further affirmed at the Society for Neuroscience annual meeting in Washington, DC, where I connected with many researchers over my enthusiasm, curiosity, and deep knowledge of the field. That was some high praise for someone who, when looking back at high school and early undergrad, could hardly remember talking unless called upon.</p>

<p>Then, in December, after marinating in these small wins, I became motivated to try to make something of my unique set of skills, and this is what I think the rest of my annual letter will be about.</p>

<h3 id="the-future-of-medicine">The future of medicine</h3>
<p>Hippocrates once said (if the records are correct), “It is far more important to know what person the disease has than what disease the person has.” These words have never rung truer. Personalized stem cell models are reshaping the landscape of precision medicine. Imagine a world where medicine is as unique as a fingerprint – that’s where I believe we’re ultimately heading. These models, tailor-made from an individual’s own cells, unravel the unique interplay between one’s genetic blueprint and disease manifestation. By differentiating induced pluripotent stem cells (iPSCs) into disease-specific cell types, we can witness the re-enactment of disease states within the distinct biological theatre of each person. It’s not just about identifying a disease anymore; it’s about understanding the patient as close to their entirety – right now, their genetic narrative. This means customizing treatments to the patient’s specific cellular and genetic predispositions, shifting from a one-size-fits-all approach to a targeted, personalized strategy.</p>

<p>Stem cell-based models, particularly when combined with in vitro multielectrode arrays (MEAs), offer unique advantages for studying neurological conditions that traditional methods cannot match. As stated above, the personalization of iPSCs is crucial in understanding the diverse ways neurological conditions can manifest in different individuals. When these iPSCs are differentiated into neuronal monolayers or three-dimensional organoid <em>mini-brains</em> and placed on MEAs, the setup provides an unparalleled platform for observing the functional characteristics of neuronal networks in real time. MEAs record the electrical activity of neurons, offering insight into the circuit-level mechanisms underlying neurological disorders, and facilitating how neurons communicate and respond to treatments, leading to more accurate drug screening and development. The non-invasive nature of MEAs allow for longitudinal studies on the same cell populations, providing valuable data on disease progression and treatment efficacy over time. The synergy between MEAs and stem cell-based models represents a significant leap in neurological research, no longer hampered by opaque and low-resolution methods, and enabling a more profound and personalized understanding of brain disorders. Stacking multiplexed functional genomics would take the entire field to a whole other level.</p>

<h3 id="so-what-does-a-phd-do-when-they-are-trying-to-break-into-a-field">So, what does a PhD do when they are trying to break into a field?</h3>

<p>Start a contract research organization, of course. A contract research organization (CRO) is a company that aids other biotechnology companies by providing outsourced research services. For example, if one lab has identified a pharmaceutical treatment that works in their rodent model, they can contact a CRO that specializes in human cell-based models using various biological assays to assess the treatment efficacy. By partnering together, the founding lab does not need to acquire the expertise and equipment themselves and can still, in a cost-effective manner, continue their research. CROs are complex entities that have some limitations in their impact and require partnerships; however, are a way that any researcher working on the cutting edge can possibly pivot after academia.</p>

<p>Whether I pursue a CRO now or a bit down the line is still uncertain. Frankly, right now, I would like some career stability after over a decade-long marathon in formal education. But if a fascinating data job doesn’t come along, I’m certainly not going to sit on my hands waiting.</p>

<p>In a matter of months, life can look like nothing you ever predicted.</p>

<p>until next year,<br />
Kartik Seyon Pradeepan</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="self-reflection" /><category term="career" /><category term="career" /><category term="self-reflection" /><category term="personal" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Starting a tradition of writing an annual letter has been on my mind for quite some time, and this year it feels especially important as I’m at a pivotal juncture in my life. Previously, my years were predictable with school activities, research, attending conferences, etc. But this year is different: I’m finishing my PhD yet facing uncertainty in what comes next professionally. It’s a time for me to look ahead, stay open to opportunities, and navigate this new phase.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The World’s Best Tiramisu Recipe</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2023/Worlds-Best-Tiramisu/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The World’s Best Tiramisu Recipe" /><published>2023-12-14T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2023-12-14T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2023/Worlds-Best-Tiramisu</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2023/Worlds-Best-Tiramisu/"><![CDATA[<p>Okay, so maybe by now you’ve probably seen that I make the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">World's Best Tiramisu</code> (see under hobbies). This is in fact a self-proclaimed title <strong>however</strong> I do think I make a mighty fine tiramisu.</p>

<p>By popular request, I have decided to bless the world with my recipe.</p>

<h3 id="equipment">Equipment</h3>
<ul>
  <li>electric whisker</li>
  <li>manual whisker</li>
  <li>espresso machine (or buy some strong coffee)</li>
  <li>1 pot</li>
  <li>3 metal bowls (helps if one of them is rimmed and as large as the pot)</li>
  <li>1 small bowl</li>
  <li>silicon spatula</li>
  <li>tea strainer</li>
  <li>approximately 9x13 inch casserole dish</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="ingredients">Ingredients</h3>
<ul>
  <li>2 cups of espresso brought to room temperature</li>
  <li>100 milliliters of Marsala</li>
  <li>a bag of at least 40 ladyfingers (always good to have a bit more)</li>
  <li>16 oz mascarpone fresh from the fridge (i.e., cold)</li>
  <li>6 egg yolks</li>
  <li>2 cups heavy whipping cream fresh from the fridge (i.e., cold)</li>
  <li>3/4 cup granulated sugar</li>
  <li>unsweetened cocoa powder</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="instructions">Instructions</h3>
<ol>
  <li>In the small bowl, stir 2 cups of room temperature espresso with 50 milliliters of Marsala.</li>
  <li>Add water to pot, place on stove, turn to medium-high heat.</li>
  <li>In the rimmed bowl, whisk together the yolks and granulated sugar. Whisk until there are clumps of sugar.</li>
  <li>Move rimmed bowl over pot (that should be steaming by now). Continue whisking over steam for 10 minutes, remove bowl from heat while whisking to cool down, place over steam again. Repeat until the yolk and sugar together until the mixture colour becomes lighter. This may take 15-20 minutes. A common test when it’s ready is to rub the mixture between your fingers and making sure it is not grainy. You may still feel some sugar but as long as it’s not very course. Remove from heat, and whisk for a few minutes to help cooldown the mixture. Set aside.</li>
  <li>In a separate metal bowl, beat together all of the mascarpone and the remaining 50 millileters of Marsala until well incorporated.</li>
  <li>Slowly introduce the cooled down yolk and sugar mixture into the mascarpone and beat with an electric mixer until well incorporated.</li>
  <li>In the third bowl, beat the cold heavy whipping cream until stiff peaks form.</li>
  <li>Using a spatula, fold 1/3 of the whipped cream into the mascarpone and yolk mix. Gently fold until incorporated. Repeat two more times for the remaining 2/3 of the whipped cream. Fold until the colours mix otherwise the mixture will become grainy.</li>
  <li>Dip the ladyfingers one by one quickly in the espresso Marsala mixture and arrange in as a single layer in a casserole dish. Spread the cream over the layer. Dip and arrange the remaining lady fingers overtop the cream layer. Spread the remaining cream overtop the second layer. Make sure that the lady fingers are completely covered.</li>
  <li>Refrigerate for at least 6 hours. The longer the better.</li>
  <li>Using the tea strainer as a duster, sprinkle as much or as little cocoa overtop your piece of the tiramisu.</li>
</ol>

<p>What makes this the best tiramisu probably comes down to technique - the ladyfingers end up being so perfectly moist that it’s like a gentle gush of coffee with every bite. Try it and let me know (or don’t).</p>

<p><img src="../../../assets/img/tiramisu.JPG" alt="Tiramisu" width="40%" /></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="tutorial" /><category term="recipe" /><category term="food" /><category term="recipe" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Okay, so maybe by now you’ve probably seen that I make the World's Best Tiramisu (see under hobbies). This is in fact a self-proclaimed title however I do think I make a mighty fine tiramisu.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Art is a way to take a snapshot of consciousness</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2023/Art-Subjective-Experience/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Art is a way to take a snapshot of consciousness" /><published>2023-10-10T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-10-10T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2023/Art-Subjective-Experience</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2023/Art-Subjective-Experience/"><![CDATA[<p>For me, that is where the beauty comes from. Being able to peer into the mind of an artist’s subjective experience. We all like to think we experience the world the same, but art is evidence that we do not.</p>

<p>I think it’s easy to dismiss certain arts as garbage, especially if it’s something that feels alien to us. But being able to understand the artist’s attempt to capture what they experience gives us a clue in how their mind works and is itself another form of beauty.</p>

<p>Daniel Tammet has Asperger’s syndrome (a form of high-functioning autism spectrum disorder; ASD), as well as savant syndrome. He possesses undreamed of numerical and linguistic abilities. He is unique as a savant because he has well-developed social skills.</p>

<p>People with ASD sometimes have synesthesia, a condition where sensory and cognitive pathways are interlinked. For Daniel Tammet, he is able to see words as colours and numbers as not only colours but also in different shapes and sizes. A great example of this is when he describes the number pi (i.e., 3.141592653…) He sees the decimals of pi as mountain landscapes consisting of a series of differently coloured numbers. While I struggle to see how this picture resembles pi, I am in awe that such an experience goes on in his head.</p>

<p><img src="../../../assets/img/Art Subjective Experience/pi.jpg" alt="Picasso Progression" width="75%" /></p>

<p>source: <a href="http://www.danieltammet.net/artwork.php">Daniel Tammet</a></p>

<p>Another great example is Dr. P described in Oliver Sacks’ “The Man Who Mistook His Wife For A Hat”. Dr. P, a patient of Oliver Sacks, was diagnosed with a case of total visual agnosia - a condition where the patient can see but cannot recognize or interpret visual information. Specifically, Dr. P had an inability to represent objects with multiple parts as well as trouble representing parts of objects. He would often mistake inanimate objects for people and struggled to recognizing people by their face.</p>

<p>Typically, when we recognize someone, we look at their face as a whole. Dr. P could no longer do this and had learned to compensate by analyzing specific features of the person, recognize people by their nose or their hair. This inability to perceive more than one object at a time, and thus unable to form a whole understanding was not limited to faces but most of his visual system. He was “lost in a world of lifeless abstractions”. What was absolutely perplexing was that he was completely unaware of his problem.</p>

<p>The reason why I bring up Dr. P is Oliver Sacks noticed something. Dr. P was a lifelong painter. He painted before his disease and into his disease. As Oliver Sacks walked past them in chronological order, what he saw first was naturalistic and realism with incredibly detail and concrete. Continuing, years later the paintings became less naturalistic and detailed, but far more abstract, even geometrical/cubist. In the final paintings, his art began resembling nonsense with mere chaotic lines and blotches of paint.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Despite this spiral into more abstract representations of visual information with the inability to form a coherent painting in his mind’s eye, Dr. P was still able to function relatively normal. How? Dr. P, a gifted painter as well as a singer, had to turn everything into a song. If disrupted, he’d completely stop and would be unable to identify his own body or clothes. He needed to distract his distorted higher-level system while his low-level vision could still interact with other processes to allow him to be functional. A case of hierarchal interconnectivity.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>What I find mystifying is Dr. P’s artistic progression through his life followed a similar progression of Picasso. <em>Makes you wonder what might have been going on in Picasso’s brain.</em></p>

<p><img src="../../../assets/img/Art%20Subjective%20Experience/Picasso%20Progression.jpg" alt="Picasso Progression" width="75%" /></p>

<p>source: <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/Damnthatsinteresting/comments/z0rm5t/the_evolution_of_picassos_style/">A Reddit Post</a></p>

<p>Dr. P’s story is a tragically beautiful case of pairting artistic style to stages of a neurological disorder. From realism to non-representational and finally abstract, “the paintings were a tragic pathological exhibit, which belonged to neurology, not art.”</p>

<p><em>How much of art is just a reflection of the artist’s pathological development?</em> Perhaps not pathological but just a standard deviation or 3 away from the norm.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="commentary" /><category term="philosophy" /><category term="art" /><category term="neuroscience" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[For me, that is where the beauty comes from. Being able to peer into the mind of an artist’s subjective experience. We all like to think we experience the world the same, but art is evidence that we do not.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Self-organization of tissue</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2023/Tissue-Self-Organization/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Self-organization of tissue" /><published>2023-09-26T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-09-26T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2023/Tissue-Self-Organization</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2023/Tissue-Self-Organization/"><![CDATA[<p>Self-organization is the spontaneous formation of overall ordered patterns and structures from the local interactions of elements in a population that have minimal patterns. Self-organization is often associated with emergence - the spontaneous appearance of an ordered property of the whole that cannot be explained by the sum of its elements.</p>

<p>Anyone familiar with developmental biology is probably comfortable with the idea of cytokine gradients and symmetry breaking. That cells can radically change along the axes of the chemical gradients that change in a distance-sensitive fashion.</p>
<blockquote>
  <p>Cytokines are signaling molecules that are secreted by one cell to have an effect on another cell. Cytokine gradients are formed due to a diffusion gradient. The cytokine is found in greater concentration the more close to the release cell and decreases with distance. Different cells can respond more/less to specific concentrations of the cytokine, which elicit different effects.
Also known as a morphogen gradient</p>
</blockquote>

<p>In biology, tissue self-organization, unlike non-living matter, involve stigmergy - a history dependency. This causes rules of interactions between elements to be dynamic and evolve in time and space in a history-dependent manner.</p>

<p><img src="../../../assets/img/Self%20Organization/morphogen%20gradient.jpg" alt="Morphogen gradient" width="75%" /></p>

<p>source: <a href="https://doi.org/10.1002/wdev.271">10.1002/wdev.271</a></p>

<p>There are three categories of tissue self-organization:</p>
<ol>
  <li>Self-assembly</li>
  <li>Self-patterning</li>
  <li>Self-morphogenesis</li>
</ol>

<p>These three occur concurrently during development and are not necessarily independent of each other.</p>

<p><strong>Self-assembly</strong> is time-evolving control of relative cellular positions due to local rules. Cells move relative to each other based on their local environment. The rules can be simple or complex.</p>

<p><strong>Self-Patterning</strong> is the spatiotemporal control of cell status by local rules without external cues. Self-assembly can contribute to this. This explains how complex tissue patterns spontaneously appear from homogenous cell populations.</p>

<p>The most common example of self-patterning in developmental biology is symmetry breaking. Often the result of stochastic processes that are stabilized by <strong>inter</strong>cellular mechanisms, e.g., the sperm entry point on the egg determines a break in symmetry.</p>

<p>As you get more self-patterning, new directional biochemical gradients and newly activated regulatory networks form, which permit further local rules for patterning. While these axes are forming, the clump of patterned cells begin to take on shape via morphogenesis.</p>

<p><strong>Self-driven morphogenesis</strong> is spatiotemporal control of intrinsic tissue mechanisms. This occurs in absence of external forces and spatial constraints. Involves complex control of locally generated internal cascades that dynamically modify cell morphology (e.g., for cell migration).</p>

<p>Observing individual cells, their behaviours are complex but quite stochastic due to extrinsic and intrinsic fluctuations. Nonetheless, as a whole, cells in a system work together to determine the pattern, shape, size, and movement of their society.</p>

<p>It’s clear that multicellular systems involve numerous regulatory components and the complexity of these interactions are beyond comprehension. These highly robust phenotypes would be difficult to be explained by rigid control of the regulatory components. Instead, perhaps there are only a limited number of control states (i.e., epigenetic attractors) that allow flexible dynamics to permit multicellularity. Identifying constraints for dynamics could reveal more about what a system can do than rigid rules currently do.</p>

<p><a href="/Flexibility-to-dogmatic-rules/"><strong>To read more about flexibility to rigid rules check out this post</strong></a></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="tutorial" /><category term="biology" /><category term="systems biology" /><category term="computation" /><category term="developmental biology" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Self-organization is the spontaneous formation of overall ordered patterns and structures from the local interactions of elements in a population that have minimal patterns. Self-organization is often associated with emergence - the spontaneous appearance of an ordered property of the whole that cannot be explained by the sum of its elements.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">“Happiness only real when shared” - Christopher McCandless (aka Alexander Supertramp)</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2023/Into-the-wild/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="“Happiness only real when shared” - Christopher McCandless (aka Alexander Supertramp)" /><published>2023-09-25T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-09-25T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2023/Into-the-wild</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2023/Into-the-wild/"><![CDATA[<p>This was the conclusion Christopher McCandless (aka Alexander Supertramp) came to during his dying moments after accidentally eating a toxin caused malabsorption leading him to a slow starvation.</p>

<p><img src="../../../assets/img/Happiness%20when%20shared/Chris%20infront%20of%20bus.jpeg" alt="Christopher McCandless infront of bus" /></p>

<p>I watched “Into the Wild” back in 2019. It retold the story of a vagabond who decided to completely break away from society, including his family. He traveled throughout the south and west US coasts, into Canada, and finally towards his goal of Alaska over 112 days of travel.</p>

<p>Now, Chris was an interesting character - athletic and intelligent, but judged others against a strong moral code (moral absolutism).</p>
<blockquote>
  <p>Moral absolutism asserts that there are certain universal moral principles by which all peoples’ actions may be judged <a href="https://ethicsunwrapped.utexas.edu/glossary/moral-absolutism#:~:text=Moral%20absolutism%20asserts%20that%20there,correct%20and%20which%20are%20incorrect.">[1]</a>. That there there is an intrinsic right and wrong, regardless of the context or consequences <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Moral_absolutism">[2]</a>.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>He lived minimally, rarely leaving his room unless needed, spending most of his time living in the books of Thoreau, Tolstoy, Emerson, and the likes.</p>

<p><img src="../../../assets/img/Happiness%20when%20shared/Thoreau%20quote.jpeg" alt="Thoreau quote" /></p>

<p>And after a series of failings around his upbringing, he began to reject the modern consumerist lifestyle and completely adopted an overly ideal and pantheistic philosophy.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Pantheism asserts that the universe and reality are manifestations of god/divinity/supreme being.</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>“You don’t need human relationships to be happy, God has placed it all around us.” - Christopher McCandless</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Watching Chris was particularly difficult because I had shared a lot of his worldview and vagabond desires at some point, albeit not quite as extreme.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>There is no greater joy than to have an endlessly changing horizon, for each day to have a new and different sun.” - Christopher McCandless</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>Ultimate freedom. An extremist. An aesthetic voyager whose home is the road. Escaped from Atlanta. Thou shalt not return, ‘cause “the West is the best.” And now after two rambling years comes the final and greatest adventure, the climatic battle to kill the false being within and victoriously conclude the spiritual revolution. Ten days and nights of freight trains and hitchhiking bring him to the great white North. No longer to be poisoned by civilization he flees, and walks along upon the land to become lost in the wild.” - Christopher McCandless</p>
</blockquote>

<p>While he made friends during his journey, many of whom grew attached to him for his aspiring yet bewildering passion (even wanting to adopt him), he was cruelly blunt with his philosophy that relationships and friendships weren’t necessary to living life to it’s fullest potential.</p>

<p>As smart as Chris apparently was, he made some idiotic judgements. He was an idealist who overly romaticized the “great Alaskan odyssey”, which left him very poorly prepared for when he was trapped along a trail due to an impassable river.</p>

<p>He had some good hunting days while stranded, but eventually degenerated into a frantic hypoglycemic delirium when food became scarce and he failed to preserve a moose before maggots.</p>

<p>He eventually resorted to seeds and berries until he accidentally took the wrong one, poisoning him.</p>

<p>During the final days, too weak to move, he realized his desire for solitary happiness in god’s gift of nature was a false ideal. Moments before zipping his weak body into his sleeping bag, he writes a single statement, “<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=x2k-oo2TT-0">Happiness only real when shared</a>”.</p>

<p><img src="../../../assets/img/Happiness%20when%20shared/Happiness%20only%20real%20when%20shared.jpeg" alt="Happiness only real when shared" /></p>

<p>Chris’s story is a tragic one. Dying alone is everyone’s greatest fear. Happiness is distributed among the relationships you share and without them, life is empty. That said, compulsive oversharing deprives experiences of meaning as much as the faux happiness of solitary life.</p>

<p>Live a life well balanced.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="commentary" /><category term="philosophy" /><category term="life" /><category term="movie" /><category term="based on true story" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This was the conclusion Christopher McCandless (aka Alexander Supertramp) came to during his dying moments after accidentally eating a toxin caused malabsorption leading him to a slow starvation.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">State Space Framework: Flexibility to dogmatic rules in biology</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2023/Flexibility-to-dogmatic-rules/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="State Space Framework: Flexibility to dogmatic rules in biology" /><published>2023-09-24T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-09-24T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2023/Flexibility-to-dogmatic-rules</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2023/Flexibility-to-dogmatic-rules/"><![CDATA[<h3 id="reconciling-incongruent-rules-of-deterministic-decision-making">Reconciling incongruent rules of deterministic decision making.</h3>

<p>In biology (and many other disciplines), linear logic pathways of causation (A-&gt;B-&gt;C) are often used to describe molecular pathways, cell fates, etc. However, these linear pathways are acutally embedded in complex networks.</p>

<p>With the influx of “omic” data, the conceptually simple idea of nested binary choices is beginning to be undermined. This comes with the realization of vastly more complicated molecular networks with many circular control loops which can be rarely explained through linear causal explanations.</p>
<blockquote>
  <p>“Omic” data is data gathered from studies that investigate biological molecules. For example, gen<strong>omic</strong> data is data related to the genes, transcript<strong>omics</strong> is data related to RNA transcripts, metabol<strong>omics</strong> is data related to metabolites, phen<strong>omics</strong> is data related to phenotype, etc. There are multiple different kinds of “omic” data, but ultimately they function to give a more precise characterization of the phenomena at the scale of the “omic” data.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><img src="../../../assets/img/State%20Space/circular%20loop.gif" alt="Circular loops" width="40%" /></p>

<p>The fundamental issue with networks of regulatory pathways is they fail to distinguish between network architecture and network dynamics. Network architecture is defined as a static collection of nodes (representing genes, proteins, etc) and arrows (representing interactions).</p>

<p>The architecture of genome-wide regulatory networks that encompass all genes is hardwired in the genomic sequence through interacting domains and regulatory proteins/elements.</p>

<p><img src="../../../assets/img/State%20Space/regulatory%20network.jpeg" alt="Regulatory Network" width="75%" /></p>

<p>source: <a href="">unknown at this moment</a></p>

<p>However, network dynamics is the concept that links network architecture and cell behaviour.</p>

<p>The idea of a state space framework aims to combine the far too simple and limiting pathway-based causality scheme with the dynamics of cellular activity to explain phenotype/behaviour. Arrows connecting genes still serve as symbols of causation, however, such linear interpretations of causal network connections fail to consider the context of the entire networks in which all these causal interactions are embedded.</p>

<p>One could theoretically follow the logic for the expression levels of gene X, however with thousands of genes involved that change their expression regarding a certain phenotype, it is very easy to quickly lose track.</p>

<p><img src="../../../assets/img/State%20Space/thinking.gif" alt="Thinking hard" /></p>

<p>The state space framework is a tool that allows us to understand these dynamics while preserving network architecture complexity. To visualize, a network state S(<em>t</em>) at time <em>t</em>, is defined by the expression levels of all the genes in the network at that specific time (<em>t</em>).</p>

<p>Think of it like a cartesian graph (akin to dimensionality reduction to find an underlying manifold), where each gene is a dimension. As we measure more variables, we increase the number of axes/dimensions (N). The state S(<em>t</em>) is a single point in the continuous, N-dimensional space, the state space, which contains <strong>ALL POSSIBLE</strong> states.</p>
<blockquote>
  <p>A manifold is a lower-dimensional subspace underlying population activity that is generally embedded in a higher-dimensional state space. Generally, you do not need to preserve the original N-dimensional state space. Rather, you can reduce dimensions to capture uncorrelated (high variance explaining) information. A manifold can also be modelled on a euclidean space.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><img src="../../../assets/img/State%20Space/SS%20cartesian.jpeg" alt="Cartesian" width="75%" /></p>

<p>source: <a href="">unknown at this moment</a></p>

<p>If we have three genes (N=3), the expression pattern of these genes at a particular cell state at time (<em>t</em>) for a behaviour, phenotype, etc is described described by the 3-variable coordinate position at that specific time (e.g., S(5 mins) = [4,3,2.5])</p>

<p>The dynamics come in when we execute all the regulatory interactions between the genes, defined by the network architecture (i.e., <em>let the cell do it’s natural thing</em>), and observe how the N-dimensional gene expression profile changes in a coordinated manner across time.</p>

<p>Each state is represented by a position. As you continue to measure the same variables across time, the position changes. The state moves along a trajectoy in the state space as the genes exert their regulatory actions onto each other according to the network architecture. Thus, the genome, via the regulatory network it encodes, constrains the movement of the state of each cell.</p>

<p>The network architecture is a static entity, because the genome does not change much in a lifetime, that constrains the alterations in the expression values of the genes. Development, homeostasis, behaviour, etc. takes place within these constraints.</p>

<p>The idea gets interesting when you find states where trajectories in the state space environment seem to converge - called attractor states. Attractor states represent stable cell states like differentiated cell types. These attractor states are characterized by a stable gene-expression profile that are often robust to small perturbations since they would attract all unstable points in their neighbourhood (because of regulatory interactions).</p>

<p>Drugs, environment, etc. can cause a state to deviate transiently but if not too large, will return to the attractor state and re-establish the associated specific gene-expression profile.</p>

<p>Since various sets of initial states can end up in the same attractor state, there are many ways to reach an attractor (which is a hallmark of stability).</p>

<p>In real systems with noise, chaos contributing to random fluctuations, the state point (S) wiggles locally in the state space.</p>

<p><img src="../../../assets/img/State%20Space/coordinated%20change.jpg" alt="Coordinated change" /></p>

<p>source: <a href="10.1371/journal.pbio.1000380">10.1371/journal.pbio.1000380</a></p>

<p>A big proponent of the state space framework/fitness landscape/combinatory phase space perspective is Stuart Kauffman. He showed that with a broad class of complex networks with random architecture (wiring), you can produce “interesting cell behaviours”. Then with evolution, you’d need only to fine-tune the state space to optimize the developmental trajectories to ensure smooth descent into attractors of mature cell types and prevent getting stuck in unused attractors of immature regions of the state space (e.g., cancer).</p>

<p>The best part of this framework is that it can be used to describe any dynamical system (e.g., cognitive/motor processes, cell behaviours, telecommunications, weather, etc). Although the big limitations are acquiring enough of the continuous data and computational cost.</p>

<p>In science it is sometimes rare to find people competent in both the math/CS side of analysis while being able to understand the biology to make appropriate interpretations. This highlights the neccessity for cross-functional collaboration. With scientific big data and multi-omic big data on the rise, I hope to see this approach used more.</p>

<h3 id="podcast-version">Podcast version</h3>
<p><a href="https://www.audacy.com/podcast/incomplete-thoughts-5d7b8/episodes/ep2-state-space-a-multidimensional-approach-to-understanding-2faf8">EP2: State Space - A multidimensional approach to understanding</a></p>

<h3 id="for-scientific-articles-on-this-topic">For scientific articles on this topic:</h3>
<p><a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC2876052/">Cell Lineage Determination in State Space: A Systems View Brings Flexibility to Dogmatic Canonical Rules</a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41583-023-00693-x">A unifying perspective on neural manifolds and circuits for cognition</a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41467-018-06560-z">Cortical population activity within a preserved neural manifold underlies multiple motor behaviors</a></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="tutorial" /><category term="commentary" /><category term="biology" /><category term="systems biology" /><category term="computation" /><category term="developmental biology" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Reconciling incongruent rules of deterministic decision making.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The cellular function of feed-forward loops (FFL) integration by OR gates</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2023/FFL-Systems-Biology/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The cellular function of feed-forward loops (FFL) integration by OR gates" /><published>2023-09-22T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-09-22T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2023/FFL-Systems-Biology</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2023/FFL-Systems-Biology/"><![CDATA[<p>The feed-forward loop (FFL) motif is a common gene regulatory network found in many organisms. The simplest form requires three nodes (gene, protein, etc.) and three regulatory interactions.</p>

<p>Typically, a transciption factor X (TF-X) interacts with TF-Y in order to regulate gene Z but TF-X can also interact with the Z promoter to activate gene Z by itself. The former pathway is called the delay/indirect pathway while the latter is known as the direct pathway.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>A transcription factor is a protein that binds to DNA at specific target sequences. It can function to make it easier (activator) or harder (repressor) for a gene to be transcribed.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><img src="../../../assets/img/FFL/pathway.png" alt="FFL pathway" /></p>

<p>TF-X and TF-Y often integrate at the Z promoter through either an AND gate (X* and Y* are <strong>BOTH</strong> required) or an OR gate (X* or T* is sufficient).</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>A promoter is a sequence of DNA ahead/upstream of the gene of interest where transcription factors (among other proteins) can bind to elicit an effect on transcription.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Both are seen in nature but confer <strong>VERY</strong> distinct properties to a system.</p>

<p>FFLs using an AND gate (AND-FFL) builds a timed delay, where there is a delay in the ON step but no delay in the OFF step.</p>

<p>FFLs using an OR gate (OR-FFL) demonstrates the opposite behaviour. OR-FFL would allow for rapid activation of a process but inactivation would take a bit of time ebcause the system would need to wait for both inputs (X* and Y*) to decrease in order to turn off the output (Z).</p>

<p>The use of AND-FFL networks is often seen in differentiation because it allows the signal to be passed if and only if the input signals are steady and persistent. This prevents differentiation from starting when the cell is not ready.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Differentiation is a process by which a cell becomes a more specific cell type. Multiple signals are necessary for differentiation to proceed in a coordinated manner to create an organism.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>On the other hand, I would speculate that OR-FFL networks can be seen in systems that have inputs that fluctuate very rapidly. For example, environmental inputs or transient molecules in a cell that act as a stress input would most likely be involved in an OR-FFL network. Unlike AND-FFL, OR-FFL has no delay in the ON step. This allows the cell to respond rapidly and only stop responding when the stressors are detected to be absent for the duration of the delay.</p>

<p>In a study, <em>E. coli</em> flagellar motor protein assembly was seen to display OR-FFL mechanism (<a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC1681456/">Kalir et al., 2005</a>). The researchers suggested that the inputs were governed by many environmental inputs such as temperature, osmotic stress, carbon starvation, etc., These factors all fluctuate rapidly and the OR-FFL allows <em>E. coli</em> to quickly swim away and only stop swimming when the stress factors are absent for an extended period of time, signifying that the new environment is safe.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Flagella are tail-like structures that allow bacteria to move in it’s environment.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Well that’s it! This network motif is by far not the only one - just one of the simpler ones. There are plenty of others (e.g., NAR, molecular ratchets, oscillators, memory devices, etc). It’s just interesting to see biological systems described as computer parts (i.e., computation). In many ways they are the same, but in many ways they’re vastly more complex and dynamic. It’s fun to fantasize about the billions of brownian input in a cell’s interactome and then to scale up complexity.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="tutorial" /><category term="biology" /><category term="systems biology" /><category term="computation" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The feed-forward loop (FFL) motif is a common gene regulatory network found in many organisms. The simplest form requires three nodes (gene, protein, etc.) and three regulatory interactions.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What is a PhD really like?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2023/What-is-a-PhD-like/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What is a PhD really like?" /><published>2023-09-20T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-09-20T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2023/What-is-a-PhD-like</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2023/What-is-a-PhD-like/"><![CDATA[<p>I recently read a post on /r/datascience that raised the question: <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">why so many people with PhDs think that's an easy pass for data science?</code></p>

<p>Initially, I found this question rather puzzling. The notion of a “PhD”, and as an “easy pass” is contradictory. Obtaining a PhD is anything but easy; it  often constitutes the most formidable intellectual challenge a person has to rise up to in their lifetime. Perhaps that is one source of confusion. So for now, I will attempt to describe <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">what does a PhD really require</code> and I will be focusing on a STEM degree (although I believe this can be applied to some non-STEM programs).</p>

<p>A PhD is also known as a Doctorate in Philosophy degree. In most fields, it is the highest academic degree a person can achieve. It typically is the result of several years of research and study in a very narrow and technical domain of knowledge. It culminates as a substantial novel contribution to scientific knowledge (e.g., increasing understanding, developing new technologies, shifting paradigms, etc.)</p>

<p><strong>Over the course of a PhD program, students will undertake a rigorous journey that requires them to:</strong></p>
<ol>
  <li>Consume thousands of pages of knowledge in their field,</li>
  <li>Identify gaps in the current understanding,</li>
  <li>Generate well-constructed hypotheses,</li>
  <li>Design carefully thought out experiments to test hypotheses,</li>
  <li>Perform (often technical and cutting-edge) experiments,</li>
  <li>Collect data (often from a variety of sources and tools),</li>
  <li>Conduct extensive analysis of the data,</li>
  <li>Formulate scientific interpretations of the results,</li>
  <li>Publish the findings in reputable peer-reviewed journals,</li>
  <li>Present their findings to other academics,</li>
  <li>And repeat this until they’ve met their degree requirements.</li>
</ol>

<p>All this is generally done with a certain level of autonomy that is alien to the structured coursework of undergraduate and master’s programs.</p>

<p><strong>Throughout their journey as a PhD student, they will encounter numerous challenges:</strong></p>
<ol>
  <li>Experiments will fail,</li>
  <li>Inter-personal conflicts between supervisors, lab members, or collaborators (or their animal model 🤣) will develop,</li>
  <li>Manuscripts will get rejected,</li>
  <li>Projects will hit dead-ends,</li>
  <li>They will feel like quitting.</li>
</ol>

<p>Yet some how, they must overcome all this and succeed.</p>

<p>Then, at the end of their degree, they will compile all their findings into a 200-page(ish) thesis that will be sent to experts in their field. They will hope they get the <em>opportunity</em> to stand in front of them and defend all the decisions they made over the last X years. Over the course of a 2 hour defense, they will look like they haven’t slept in 2 days. Jokes aside, I guarantee you that every STEM PhD holder has gone through this. A PhD is grueling, frustrating, anything but easy, yet often rewarding in retrospect (see <a href="https://www.rei.com/blog/climb/fun-scale">type 2 fun</a>).</p>

<p>Hopefully you can understand that a PhD is not something you should be willing to do unless you truly enjoy the pursuit of knowledge.</p>

<p>As to <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">what makes people with PhDs more adept at data science right out of school?</code>, I will address that question in a separate post.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="personal" /><category term="PhD" /><category term="self-reflection" /><category term="career" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I recently read a post on /r/datascience that raised the question: why so many people with PhDs think that's an easy pass for data science?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How to embed Jupyter Notebooks (.ipynb) into Jekyll (AcademicPages)</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/posts/2023/09/Convert-Juypter-Notebook-to-Jekyll/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to embed Jupyter Notebooks (.ipynb) into Jekyll (AcademicPages)" /><published>2023-09-19T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-09-19T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/posts/2023/09/Convert-Juypter-Notebook-to-Jekyll</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/posts/2023/09/Convert-Juypter-Notebook-to-Jekyll/"><![CDATA[<p>Since creating this personal website, I’ve wanted to find a way to embed python notebook snippets to showcase my projects and hopefully eventually create tutorials that people can learn from. To do this, you need to convert python notebook files (.ipynb) into markdown (.md) along with all the embeded images.</p>

<ol>
  <li>Create a <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">_notebooks</code> directory inside the master folder. This is where you should be putting your jupyter notebooks.</li>
  <li>Using terminal, navigate to the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">_notebooks</code> directory and type the following command to convert it to markdown <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">jupyter nbconvert &lt;name of file&gt;.ipynb --to markdown</code></li>
  <li>Move the converted products (which should be the .md file along with a folder containing an image outputs) to <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">_posts</code> folder.</li>
  <li>Add the Jekyll AcademicPages metadata.</li>
  <li>Add <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">../</code> infront of every image path. This will allow the path of the image (which is in the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">_posts</code> folder) to be read. Alternatively, you can place the images in the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">_images</code> folder but will need to adjust the path accordingly.</li>
</ol>

<p>There you have it! Pretty simple. Lets you turn your website into an all-in-one repository for all your projects.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="tutorial" /><category term="data science" /><category term="python" /><category term="code" /><category term="jupyter-notebooks" /><category term="jekyll" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Since creating this personal website, I’ve wanted to find a way to embed python notebook snippets to showcase my projects and hopefully eventually create tutorials that people can learn from. To do this, you need to convert python notebook files (.ipynb) into markdown (.md) along with all the embeded images.]]></summary></entry></feed>